Okay, today's דף Daf is ע"ב, Ayin Bet, 72. And we pick
up in the bottom of ע"א, Ayin Alef, עמוד ב׳, Amud Bet,
and we are dealing with a important question, which is having ריבית
Ribis lent with between two Jews and a non-Jew and how those
things can work out. So yesterday we dealt with the important issue
about is there a Rabbinic restriction on lending to a non-Jew with
interest? And רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam found ways to say that there
was not even though the גמרא Gemara seemed to be that there
were certain limits to that. Here we come to an issue which
is hugely important in the Middle Ages as well, which is is
there ways that you could basically use a non-Jew as a cutout
man and basically lend to a Jew with interest through a non-Jew?
So the גמרא Gemara describes two scenarios. You know what, maybe we'll
just do it very quickly again from the two dots, so let's
be quick about it. So it's about ten lines from the top
of the two dots. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, מלוה ישראל מעותיו של נכרי מדעת הנכרי אבל לא
מדעת ישראל. Malve Yisrael me'otav shel Nochri mida'at haNochri aval lo mida'at
Yisrael. A Jew can borrow money of a non-Jew with a non-Jew's
sort of involvement or knowledge but not only straight with the Jew.
כיצד, Keitzad, what does this mean? ישראל שלווה מעות מן הנכרי בריבית
וביקש להחזירם לו. Yisrael shelava ma'os min haNochri beRibis uvikeish lehachaziram lo.
So Reuben borrowed money from a Christopher with ריבית Ribis and he
wanted to give it back to Christopher. מצא ישראל אחר, Matza Yisrael
acher, Shimon found and ואמר לו, ve'amar lo, תנם לי ואני אעלה
לך כדרך שאתה מעלה לו. tneim li va'ani a'aleh lach kederech she'atah
ma'aleh lo. You still Reuben pay Christopher, you lend me the money
you now want to return with interest or whatever, you now you
borrowed a thousand you're ready to return twelve hundred, give it to
me, I'll pay you interest on that loan and then you can
continue paying interest to Christopher there. So obviously that's forbidden, אסור, assur,
because then Shimon is paying interest to Reuben. ואם העמידו אצל נכרי,
Ve'im he'emido etzel Nochri,
but if Shimon says to Reuben, Reuben come bring me with you
to Christopher and then Reuben comes and they're all in front of
Christopher and Reuben says here's the twelve hundred dollars I owe you
I'm now even and Shimon says no no no give them to
me and I'll owe you Christopher the money. So in that case
מותר, mutar, it's permissible, because Reuben gives the money that he should
have given to Christopher he gives it to Shimon in Christopher's presence
and that effectively means that Shimon now is the one who owes
money to Christopher and who is paying interest to Christopher. That's okay,
okay? מותר. Mutar. וכן, Vechein,
and the same would be in the reverse. נכרי שלווה מעות מן
הישראל בריבית וביקש להחזירם לו. Nochri shelava ma'os min haYisrael beRibis uvikeish
lehachaziram lo.
So Christopher here borrowed money from Reuben and wanted to pay back
Reuben. That's okay. מצא ישראל אחר, Matza Yisrael acher, Shimon now finds
Christopher ואמר לו, ve'amar lo, תנם לי ואני אעלה לך כדרך שאתה
מעלה לו. tneim li va'ani a'aleh lach kederech she'atah ma'aleh lo.
You give me that money, I will pay you Christopher, you know,
the money plus interest and then you'll continue to pay your loan
off that loan off to Reuben. So that's okay, because Shimon is
paying Christopher. So in that's okay, מותר. mutar. ואם העמידו אצל ישראל,
Ve'im he'emido etzel Yisrael, if they all went to Reuben and Shimon
says they're all standing in front of Reuben and Shimon says Christopher
give me the money and fine good now I'll pay Reuben that's
obviously forbidden because now Shimon is paying Reuben interest. ואם העמידו אצל
ישראל, Ve'im he'emido etzel Yisrael, העמידו אצל ישראל אסור, He'emido etzel Yisrael
assur,
it's forbidden. Okay so all that makes sense sort of, but the
one thing that we have to figure out is how when they're
standing in front Reuben and Shimon are standing in front of Christopher
and Shimon says to Reuben just give me the money Christopher says
and it's all under Christopher's auspices but in the end of the
day Christopher didn't give him the money, Reuben did. So how does
that make it that now the loan has shifted to between Shimon
and Christopher? So that's the question. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בשלמא סיפא לחומרא. Bishlama seifa lechumra.
I get in the end here maybe we'll draw the two cases.
Okay so case number one is okay
Reuben
here's Christopher okay he borrows money from Christopher okay he is the
lender and then okay so if Shimon comes and basically says I'll
pay you and then you pay him that's obviously אסור assur because
then he's paying interest to Reuben okay but if Shimon and Reuben
come together and Shimon says and in the presence of Christopher Reuben
who has the money to give back here this will be the
giving back of the money Reuben has the money to give back
rather than giving back to Christopher in Christopher's presence gives it to
Shimon that is okay that effectively means that now it's like Christopher
lent the money to Shimon and now Shimon is paying Christopher with
interest. But the question is going to be how it just went
straight from Reuben to Shimon what does the how does that make
it as if Shimon now owes the money to Christopher? But that
case is allowed okay that's the case number one where if they
do it in Christopher's presence it's allowed. Case number two is that
Reuben is the one who has the money he lends it to
Christopher okay if Shimon were to pay Christopher to pay Reuben that
would be fine because then right then it's paying to the non-Jew
but instead they both come in front of Reuben okay they both
come in front of Reuben. and if Christopher's now, rather than give
the money back to ראובן, Reuven, gives the money to שמעון. Shimon.
Okay, in that case, it's no good, because it's like now שמעון
Shimon owes the money to ראובן, Reuven, and the debt is now,
right, when it's in that person's presence, it's like he paid that
person and now that person lent to the other person. Okay, so
this case is no good, right, this case is אסור, assur, okay,
and this case, this case is אסור, assur, this case is מותר.
mutar. But they both work on the same principle that when it's
in that person's presence, it's like the loan has now, it's like
the loan was paid back and lent to the other person. So
the question is going to be, yeah, but who says that it
gets to be that way? Why just because it's in this person's
presence? In the end of the day, שמעון Shimon got the money
from Christopher. And in the end of the day, here שמעון Shimon
got the money from ראובן. Reuven. So what a, what made it
that it's now like the loan is to the other person? So
that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. Let's take a look.
Okay, who's the, who's the interest being paid? Well, ah,
so that's of course the big question which תוספות Tosafot asks, which
is like, why does any of this matter? At the end of
the day, the question is that who's getting the interest? But it
sort of matters because, if you say that, let's say we either
say that in this case. Okay, Christopher is going to continue to
get his five percent, right? But if you view it as if
the loan never transferred, then it's always that ראובן Reuven owes the
money to Christopher and owes the five percent to Christopher and if
שמעון Shimon happens to be the one paying Christopher, what he's really
doing is, we could conceptualize it as, if let's say they didn't
do it in the presence of Christopher, right? So basically שמעון Shimon
now owes money to ראובן Reuven and he owes interest to ראובן
Reuven and ראובן Reuven owes it to Christopher. So if שמעון Shimon
were to go ahead and take the, take now the, you know,
the five dollars of interest this week and bring it over to
Christopher, is he paying Christopher the money he owes Christopher, or is
he paying money that he owes ראובן Reuven and that ראובן Reuven
owes Christopher? So, right, at the end of the day, the money
whether it's going this way or this way, Christopher's going to get
his interest. Right, so the simplest way to understand the conclusion is
that it's the guy who's whoever's paying who the interest. Whoever's handing
it over? But I don't know, maybe I'm just doing, maybe I
owe it to ראובן Reuven and I'm just doing a favor? Why
should I bother, I understand. But conceptually what we have to do
is we have to say, you know, we don't start at the
end, we start at the beginning. Who lent the money is the
person who the money is owed to. Who is paying the interest,
delivering the interest, we're going to, we're going to frame that, you
know, we're not going to determine who owes the money based on
who happens to be handing over the interest. We're going to frame
it in terms of who lent the money. So, but I understand
the question. It's a very reasonable question, but let's see, right, everything
that Dov's asking, at the end of the day, right, in these
cases, right, the person who originally originated the loan is taking in
the interest. But what the גמרא's Gemara saying is it doesn't, we're
not just going to say just by virtue of the fact that
he's paying him interest means that that's the nature, that that's the
loan. Theoretically, the loan could be this way and, and it's just
that שמעון Shimon is just cutting it short and just, you know,
just giving Christopher the money that he owes ראובן Reuven that ראובן
Reuven owes Christopher. So we have to first determine whose money is
it and who made the loan. And in that context, I don't
understand why scenario number two is אסור. assur. In other words, שמעון's
Shimon giving a lump sum to ראובן, Reuven, doesn't do with the
loan, the loan went between ראובן Reuven and Christopher. Yeah, but then
in ראובן's Reuven presence, Christopher took the money he owed ראובן, Reuven,
the entire totality of the sum and in ראובן's Reuven presence handed
it over to שמעון. Shimon. So we're conceptualizing that as if Christopher
paid ראובן Reuven back and now ראובן Reuven lent the money to
שמעון. Shimon. That's the basic underlying assumption. When the lump sum is,
not just the interest payment, the entire amount is handed over in
the presence of the lender to another party and presumably with the,
with the approval of the lender, it's as if the whole loan
has now been made anew to the new person. That's the חידוש,
chiddush, okay? But okay, and therefore here it's אסור assur because now
it's a Jew paying a Jew interest. It's not this, it's that.
And here it's מותר mutar because it's a Jew paying a non-Jew
interest. Okay, but Dov is right to point out like in either
way, you got somebody paying, you know, the actual money being handed
over goes this way. Yes, that is true, but we have to
ask, what does that handing over of cash represent? Does it represent
the loan you owe directly or is it indirect? Okay, so we
have to start by saying whose money did שמעון Shimon take? Okay,
and what we're saying is if it's done in the presence of
the original lender, it's like he took the lender's money. Okay, so
now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, but why is that true
just because it's in that person's presence? So let's take a look.
בשלמא, Bishlama, says the גמרא, Gemara, סיפא לחומרא. seifa lechumra. I get
this case, you're saying it's אסור. assur. It's like he got the
money from ראובן Reuven and it's a Jew owing a non-Jew money
and paying interest. Fine, you want to be strict, be strict. Okay,
but so, you know, even though he never got any cash from
Reuven, we'll think it, we'll treat it as if he did. אלא
רישא Ella reisha
כיון דאין שליחות לנכרי kivan d'ein shlichus l'nochri איהו ניהו דקשקיל מיניה
ריביתא ihu nihu de'kashakil minei ribisa But in this case, when Reuven
hands over the money to Shimon, he can't be a שליח shaliach
for Christopher. It's in Christopher's presence and Reuven says, "Christopher, I got
this, I got all the money I owe you." Christopher says, "It's
fine, give it over to Shimon. Shimon'll now owe me the money."
Okay? But Reuven can't be Christopher's שליח shaliach There's no שליחות shlichus
with a non-Jew. So when he hands it over to Shimon, he's
not handing it over in Christopher's capacity, right? Because there's no sense
of being an agent for a non-Jew. So when Reuven hands it
over to Shimon, it's just Reuven's money that's going to Shimon. So
Christopher never lent Shimon the money. Okay, if you want to be
מחמיר machmir about it and say don't pay, fine, but to be
מקיל meikel and say now you can pay Christopher interest even though
you only got money from Shimon, how's that possible? Good question, right?
You understand the question, right? All right, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אלא רישא Ella reisha כיון דאין שליחות לנכרי kivan d'ein
shlichus l'nochri איהו ניהו דקשקיל מיניה ריביתא ihu nihu de'kashakil minei ribisa
How does this work? Where Reuven could take the money from Christopher
in case one, and Reuven could make Shimon his שליח shaliach Well,
no. The only thing that could happen is Reuven could give the
money to Christopher and Christopher could give it to Shimon. Exactly, but
that's not what happened. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב אחא בריה דרב איקא Amar Rav Huna
bar Manoach mishmei de'Rav Acha brei de'Rav Ika הכא במאי עסקינן כגון
שאמר לו הניחם על גבי קרקע
ויפטר hacha bemai askinan kegon she'amar lo hanicham al gabi karka veyipater
No, no, no. He didn't say, "you go ahead and give it
to Shimon for me." What Christopher said to Reuven was, "Christopher, that
money, don't bother handing it to me, my hands are full, put
it down on the table, and then you're free from your loan."
Okay, so Reuven put it on the table, he was free from
his loan, he walked away. And then Christopher said to Shimon, "Shimon,
you want to owe me the money? Pick it up. Now you
owe me the money." Okay, so it wasn't that Reuven gave it
to Shimon as Christopher's agent. Reuven first, you know, finished with Christopher,
ended the loan, and then Christopher gave it over
to
Shimon. שיעבודא דרבי נתן Shibuda de'Rabbi Natan Right. We usually say that.
Well we do. Questions what we say about a non-Jew, but that's
exactly why, because of that, yes, but even when we say if
A owes B and B owes C, you can pay directly, you're
still paying conceptually through the other person, right? So if it was
true that Shimon owed Reuven and Reuven owed Christopher, Shimon could not
pay Christopher because he's still paying the money he owes Reuven and
it's ending at Christopher. So it's still the fundamental interest payment is
to Reuven. It doesn't conceptually eliminate Reuven. It just means again it
could be delivered to the person at the end of the road,
but conceptually it's still working through the middle stages. What? That would
work for me because I think it's like you represent the money.
Exactly, you're being very consistent. But you're right, that's a very relevant
principle, but that even that principle still maintains it at a conceptual
level the way it's sort of, you know, working. So initially Christopher
in scenario one, Christopher gives Reuven $100. Yeah. Yeah, and then Reuven's
gotta pay Christopher back $150 let's say. So what happens? He got
the $150, he puts it on the table, and Christopher then says
to Shimon, "pick it up and give it to me." Pick no,
not give it to me. "You want to borrow $150 from me?
Go ahead, pick it up. Now you owe me $150 with 5%
interest" or whatever it is. Okay, now you could ask in that
case, even though Christopher exempted Reuven from the rest of the loan,
when did Christopher ever take possession of the money? So that's an
interesting question, but anyway let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes from
this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי ei hachi says
the גמרא Gemara
מאי למימרא mai l'meimra So what's the חידוש chiddush So there's no
חידוש chiddush that because it's in the presence of Christopher, it's like
the money was transferred. If he did the same, Reuven paid off
the loan and then Christopher lent it to Shimon. So there's no
חידוש chiddush here. אי הכי מאי למימרא ei hachi mai l'meimra says
the גמרא Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב פפא
ella amar Rav Papa כגון דנטל ונתן ביד kegon d'natal v'nasan b'yad
So that's like even less of a חידוש chiddush Christopher took the
money from Reuven, or Reuven handed it over, and then he lent
it to Shimon. Okay, again, that's no חידוש chiddush at all. So
big deal, so now Shimon owes Christopher the money. ודקאתי מאי למימרא
v'de'ka'asi mai l'meimra so what's the חידוש chiddush מהו דתימא אימאי צורת
נכרי גופיה כי עביד אדעתא דישראל קגמר ויהיב קא משמע לן Mah
d'teima imai tzuras nochri gufeih ki avid ada'ata d'Yisrael kagammar v'yahiv ka
mashma lan
Maybe I would have said like this: Reuven and Shimon come in
front, Reuven says to Christopher, "I got the money to pay you
back but my friend Shimon here would like to borrow that money
now." So Christopher says fine. So he takes the money from Reuven
and he hands it to Shimon. So I say well maybe there
Christopher was actually just acting as Reuven's שליח shaliach Meaning maybe that
wasn't that Reuven paid Christopher and Christopher lent the money, maybe it
was Reuven asked Christopher that Shimon should borrow the money now so
Christopher was just actually, you know, helping out Reuven and it's still
fundamentally owed to Reuven. That's a little far-fetched, okay, to still you
know, but nevertheless that's the whole חידוש chiddush קא משמע לן Ka
mashma lan not that way. Okay.
The bottom line is what the גמרא Gemara says is it doesn't
work just to do it in the presence of Christopher. You actually
have to pay off Christopher and then have Christopher pay שמעון. Shimon.
Okay, so I want to just pause here for a moment and
say, okay, this by the way though becomes the basic a basic
way in which a Jew is able to lend a Jew with
interest without a היתר עסקה, heter iska, okay, which is basically that
it wasn't this case actually because this case the non-Jew had the
money, it's this case. So basically, ראובן Reuven pays Christopher, Christopher pays
שמעון, Shimon, and then this gets back to the important point that
you're saying דב, Dov, שמעון Shimon might even be able in that
case to make direct payments to ראובן Reuven because what he's really
doing is he's paying Christopher and Christopher's paying ראובן, Reuven, right? So
but but anyway but this becomes the case where if you don't
do it in the presence of ראובן, Reuven, right? Now the question
is can ראובן Reuven call in שמעון Shimon comes through and can
I borrow a hundred dollars and ראובן Reuven says sure, like you
know they have the שבת גוי Shabbos Goy so they have the
ריבית גוי. Ribbis Goy. Sure, let me call Christopher in from the
other room. Christopher, come in, שמעון Shimon wants to borrow some money.
And then you hand it to Christopher, Christopher hands it to שמעון.
Shimon. Is that okay? Or do we say no, no, no, if
it's in his presence it's no good. That gets to the question
of is the issue here presence or only when the money is
actually physically handed over and then re-handed over. So this might be,
depending on the fact that now we said it's not enough to
do it in the other person's presence, you have to actually hand
the money and then it has to be handed again, ראובן Reuven
might even be able to call in שמעון Shimon and do all
of this in his presence. Okay, but if you but if you
can't do that because then that's too much like he lent the
money on condition that ראובן Reuven pick it up. ראובן, Reuven, well,
right, ראובן Reuven says to שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon says I want
to borrow a hundred dollars, ראובן Reuven says okay, Christopher will go
pay you a visit a little bit later today. And then he
calls in Christopher, he gives him the money, and Christopher goes and
Christopher lends שמעון Shimon the money and there you go, right? Christopher
goes to see Christopher table
three. Exactly. So that anyway so that becomes how right,
so then it becomes a really interesting question, right, because maybe he
maybe once it's done this way maybe he could maybe maybe, I'm
not saying yes, but maybe he could pay ראובן Reuven directly because
it's conceptually he owes the money to Christopher and he's just delivering
Christopher's money to ראובן, Reuven, right? So Christopher becomes the total like
cutout man. Okay. All right, let's take a look now. Now we're
going to try to have another answer, another answer about how this
could work even though the money was not paid back to Christopher.
That solves all the antisemitism problems. Christopher likes שמעון Shimon and ראובן
Reuven and everybody lives happily. Exactly, it's Jewish history in a nutshell.
Exactly.
So now so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, רב
אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar. Now we're going to be back to
trying to figure out how this works since you know since שמעון
Shimon didn't get the money directly from ראובן. Reuven. We said he
did, we said ראובן Reuven paid it and שמעון Shimon paid it,
but if not how does it work? So רב אשי אמר כי
אמרינן אין שליחות לנכרי הני מילי בתרומה אבל בכל התורה כולה יש
שליחות לנכרי. Rav Ashi amar, ki aminan ein shlichus lenochri, hani mili
bitruma, aval bechol hatorah kullah yesh shlichus lenochri.
No,
a non-Jew can be a שליח shaliach for a Jew. So in
this case I'm or a Jew can be a שליח shaliach for
a non-Jew. So in this case when Christopher says to ראובן Reuven
give the money to
שמעון, Shimon, ראובן Reuven acting on behalf of Christopher and it works,
there is שליחות. shlichus. So the גמרא Gemara says, אד-רב אשי ברותא
היא. ad-Rav Ashi brusa hi. Or בדותא היא. bedusa hi.
The גמרא Gemara sometimes does not like רב אשי, Rav Ashi, he's
a very creative thinker and the גמרא Gemara sometimes doesn't want to
tolerate his idea. So basically it says that's foolishness, that's nonsense. מאי
שנא תרומה דלא, mai shna truma delo,
why can there not be שליחות shlichus with a Jew and a
non-Jew by תרומה, truma, דכתיב dichsiv it says, אתם גם אתם, atem
gam atem, it says, כן תרימו גם אתם תרומת השם. ken tarimu
gam atem trumas Hashem.
Also you should take the תרומה. truma. So what's the also? Also
means even your שליח. shaliach. But it says גם אתם gam atem
which means your שליח shaliach has to be like you. מה אתם
בני ברית, ma atem bnei bris,
the same way you're part of the covenant, אף שלוחכם נמי בני
ברית. af shluchachem nami bnei bris.
So since that's true by תרומה truma that it can't a non-Jew
cannot be the שליח shaliach or the משלח, meshaleach, שליחות דכל התורה
כולה נמי מתרומה גמרינן לה. shlichus dechol hatorah kulla nami mitruma gamrinan
lah.
So שליחות shlichus for all the rest of the תורה Torah is
based on תרומה. truma. So so of course maybe רב אשי Rav
Ashi didn't agree with that. Maybe רב אשי Rav Ashi thought there
was other things for שליחות, shlichus, whole second פרק perek of קידושין.
Kiddushin. Anyway, אלא דרב אשי ברותי. ella deRav Ashi brusi. רב אשי
Rav Ashi is foolishness. Now of course you could have also made
a distinction between ritual matters like writing or giving a גט, get,
taking תרומה truma and monetary matters, right? Monetary matters to say, you
know, you'll give the money to him and it'll be given in
my behalf or whatever is a very different type of a שליחות.
shlichus. Anyway, איכא דאמרי ika d'amri others say, אמר רב אשי, amar
Rav Ashi, כי אמרינן אין שליחות לנכרי הני מילי אינהו לדידן. ki
aminan ein shlichus lenochri hani mili inhu ledidan.
When do we say there's no שליחות shlichus for a non-Jew that
means a non-Jew cannot be our שליח. shaliach. אבל אנן לדידהו הוינא
להו שליח. aval anan ledidhu havina lehu shaliach. For us to be
their שליח, shaliach, that works. So here when ראובן Reuven gives the
money to שמעון, Shimon, he's a שליח shaliach for Christopher. Christopher can't
be ראובן's Reuven's שליח, shaliach, but ראובן Reuven can be Christopher's שליח.
shaliach. Okay. ואד-רב אשי ברותא היא. vad-Rav Ashi brusa hi. The גמרא
Gemara again, no that's foolishness, that's nonsense. מאי שנא אינהו לדידן דלא,
mai shna inhu ledidan delo, they can't be our שליח shaliach דלא
delo that can't be. They can, דכתיב, dichtiv, אתם גם אתם, atem
gam atem, you even you, לרבות שלוחכם, l’rabos shluchechem, your שליח shaliach
has to be like you. מה אתם בני ברית אף שלוחכם בני
ברית, Mah atem bnei bris af shluchechem bnei bris, namely you are
part of the covenant, your שליח shaliach has to be part of
the covenant. איהו לדידן נמי, Inhu l'didan nami, for us to be
their שליח shaliach also. מה אתם בני ברית קאמר, Mah atem bnei
bris ka’amar, it starts with the אתם. atem. It starts with that
the משלח meshaleach has to be Jewish. For שליחות shlichus to work
it has to be אתם גם אתם. atem gam atem. It has
to be you, Jews, are the משלח meshaleach and גם אתם gam
atem and even your שליח shaliach has to be Jewish. אלא הדר
ביה רב אשי, Ela hadar beih Rav Ashi,
so the גמרא Gemara rejects Rav Ashi. I always liked the Rav
Ashis, they're always very creative. But the גמרא Gemara rejects him. רבינא
אמר, Ravina amar, now רבינא Ravina says: נהי דשליחות לנכרי לית ליה,
Nehi deshlichus l’nochri leis leih, it's true that a נכרי nochri cannot
be שליח shaliach or משלח. meshaleach. זכייה מדרבנן אית ליה, Zechiah miderabbanan
is leih, but it can work with rabbinic with זכייה. zechiah. Remember
like זכין לאדם שלא בפניו? zachin l'adam shelo befanav? So therefore, what
Christopher says to Reuven is—he doesn't say be my שליח. shaliach. What
he says to Shimon is, he says the following: Shimon, he says,
take my—take the money from Reuven and you be זוכה zocheh when
Reuven gives you the $1,500, you're taking of that money, you'll be
קונה koneh it for me. Okay, so Shimon is going to be
זוכה zocheh in the money on behalf of Christopher. So there's not
going to be a שליחות. shlichus. Okay, by the way, the שליחות
shlichus could have also worked that Christopher wasn't saying to Reuven be
my שליח shaliach to give it to Shimon, he could have said
to Shimon be my שליח shaliach to accept the payment from Reuven.
Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says fine, שליחות shlichus doesn't work. But
at least this idea of זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo
befanav, which is really saying let's shift from the ritual realm, if
you would, to the monetary realm, all we have to do is
take possession of the money for somebody. That's a principle of זכין.
zachin. It's not like שליח shaliach for גט. get. So when Reuven
gives the money to Shimon, Shimon will take possession of it for
Christopher, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l’adam shelo befanav, and now it's
Christopher's money in Shimon's hands, and now Shimon is going to keep
it to himself and now he borrowed it from Christopher. So Christopher
is being מזכה mezakeh Shimon?
No, Reuven is being מזכה mezakeh the money to Shimon, and Shimon
is being קונה koneh it, זוכה zocheh in it for Christopher. Reuven
is giving the money to Shimon, Shimon is being קונה koneh it
for Christopher. But Christopher can't be in the room? Yes he can,
or שלא בפניו. shelo befanav. Well, even שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, not
only שלא בפניו. shelo befanav. Okay. All right. And then now Shimon
has Christopher's money because he was קונה koneh it for Christopher, and
now he's—now he's going to put it in his pocket and now
he borrowed it from Christopher. Okay. So זכייה מדרבנן אית ליה, Zechiah
miderabbanan is leih, מידי דהוה אקטן, midi d’hava akatan, like we find
by a minor. קטן לאו אע"ג דלית ליה שליחות, Katan lav af
al gav d’leis leih shlichus, even though a קטן katan can't be
a שליח, shaliach, אית ליה זכייה, is leih zechiah, you can be
זוכה zocheh something on behalf of a קטן. katan. Like I can
say to me, here, I gotta give this—I want to give this
to my son, his בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah gift, it's going to
be on שבת, Shabbos, can't do a קנין kinyan on שבת, Shabbos,
he's not—he's not בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah yet, he'll be בר מצוה
Bar Mitzvah in two days. Dope, take possession of it for my
son. I could do that, right? Even though his son can't make
me a שליח, shaliach, I can be זוכה zocheh in something for
a minor. So you can be זוכה zocheh in something for somebody
even though there's no שליחות. shlichus. מדרבנן הכא נמי לא שנא. Miderabbanan
hacha nami lo shna.
So Shimon can't be Christopher's שליח, shaliach, but he can be זוכה
zocheh in the money that Reuven gives him on behalf of Christopher.
So the גמרא Gemara says: ולא היא, V'lo hi, that's not true.
זוכה Zocheh in the money for Christopher? Well, Reuven is going to
give him money and he'll be זוכה zocheh in it, he'll take
possession of it on behalf of Christopher. Okay, so you're זוכין zochin
for Christopher? For Christopher, right. Exactly. Okay, so the same way he
could be זוכה zocheh in that money for Reuven's under-age son, he
could be זוכה zocheh in that money for Christopher. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says: הכא נמי לא שנא. Hacha nami lo shna. ולא
היא, V'lo hi, that's not true. ישראל אתי לכלל שליחות, Yisrael ati
l’chlal shlichus, עכו"ם לא אתי לכלל שליחות. akum lo ati l’chlal shlichus.
The minor son will eventually be an adult and be able to
make a שליח, shaliach, and this raises an interesting question: is זכייה
zechiah based on שליחות shlichus or based on something else? So the
גמרא Gemara here sounds like it's based on שליחות. shlichus. So זכייה
zechiah only works for somebody for whom eventually will be in the
פרשה parsha of שליחות. shlichus. Since Christopher will never be in that
פרשה, parsha, could never make Shimon a שליח shaliach to take the
money for him, so Shimon also can't be זוכה zocheh in the
money for him. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says there is no
real formal structure that Reuven, just by directly paying the money to
Shimon, means that Shimon is getting the money from Christopher. Reuven can't
be Christopher's שליח, shaliach, Shimon can't be Christopher's שליח, shaliach, Shimon can't
do זוכין. zochin. There's no real way that if it's just in
his presence, it really is as if it was paid back and
whatever. Well, why did we just—why did we just reject זוכין? zochin?
Because we want זכייה zechiah only to be limited to cases where
somebody eventually will be in a category of שליחות. shlichus. Okay. So
conceptually, exactly. No, it's a funny thing, like, you know, זכין zachin
is like—זכייה, zechiah, like, who's זוכה? zocheh? Who would be זוכה zocheh
there? Shimon? Shimon. No, Shimon is זוכה zocheh in it on behalf
of Christopher, yeah. Yeah. Funny. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabbanan, fine. That was the end
of. The point תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* made is an excellent one and
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is discussing it from who you happen to be
handing over the payments to does not in itself define who the
money is owed to, right? And figuring out who really was the
owner of the money and who borrowed money from whom. And that
getting into that very relevant issue in terms of the Middle Ages
of a Jew borrowing from a Jew through a non-Jew.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, תנו רבנן
Tanu Rabbanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*. ישראל שלוה מעות מן הנכרי בריבית וזקפן עליו
במלוה *Yisrael she-lavah maos min ha-nochri beribbis, ve-zakfan alav bemilveh*. Okay, שמעון
*Shimon* again borrowed money from Christopher, and he, and now, you know,
it was a thousand dollars, five percent interest, whatever, a week or
whatever, at the end of, you know, at the end of the
year it's now twelve hundred dollars. Okay, so, and now what שמעון
*Shimon* says to, what ראובן *Reuven* says to, to שמעון *Shimon* is,
you know what? Let's redo this. By now, principal plus interest, I
owe you twelve hundred dollars. Let's just write a new שטר shtar
*shtar* that I owe you twelve hundred dollars. Okay, like we're consolidating
the debt or whatever we're doing, all right? So made it into
as if it was a brand new loan now of twelve hundred
dollars. All right. ונתגייר *Ve-nisgayer*. And now, Christopher converts. Okay, we'll
have to come up with a new name for him. חיים *Chaim*.
So now, can ראובן *Reuven* pay חיים *Chaim* the twelve hundred dollars?
Right? He could have paid it to him when he was Christopher,
but can he pay it to him now? Is that a thousand
dollars plus two hundred dollars of interest? Or because they converted it,
converted it, because they, I guess they converted it to a twelve
hundred dollar loan, it's just a straight twelve hundred dollars he owes
him, it's not interest anymore, and he can pay it to him.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this, אם קודם שנתגייר זקפן
עליו במלוה גובה את הקרן וגובה את הריבית *Im kodem shenisgayer zakfan
alav bemilveh, goveh es haker ve-goveh es haribbis*. Then he can pay
חיים *Chaim* the full twelve hundred dollars because it was just a
straight twelve hundred dollars he owed the person. ואם אחר שנתגייר זקפן
עליו במלוה *Ve-im achar shenisgayer zakfan alav bemilveh*, but if it was,
it was changed into a loan after the, the conversion, after he
became חיים *Chaim*, so at the moment he became חיים *Chaim*, he
owed this person a thousand dollars plus two hundred dollars of interest,
and now he just turned it into a twelve hundred dollar loan.
But now, nevertheless, it's defined in terms of the fact that initially
it was a thousand plus two hundred when this guy was Jewish,
when this guy was חיים *Chaim*, when it was אסור *assur* to
take interest. Okay, so in that case, in that case, גובה את
הקרן ואינו גובה את הריבית goveh et ha'keren ve'eino goveh et ha'ribbit,
*goveh es haker ve-eino goveh es haribbis*, you only pay the principal,
you do not pay the two hundred. What I find fascinating, by
the way, I mean, maybe not so fascinating, but it's worth pointing
out, is that, you know, we say this idea that a גר
שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי *ger shenisgayer ke-katan shenolad dami*, it's like he's
a new person. But it sounds like the, in terms of monetary
issues, the debt, you know, money he owes people, that people owe
him or whatever, that continues, right? That doesn't change just because his
personal status has changed. Well, we'll talk about that in a minute.
Somebody asked me a great question which I didn't have a chance
to look at. He's taking a group of, of conversion candidates to
Israel, and they're going to do their conversion in Israel, and they're
going to visit the כותל *Kotel* with them, you know, before the
conversion, and then they're going to visit after the conversion. So when
he visits with them after the conversion, do they have to do
קריעה *keriah*? Because if you've seen the כותל *Kotel* within thirty days,
you don't have to do קריעה *keriah*. But they've seen it within
thirty days, but when they saw it before, they were not Jewish,
right? It's like, I said to him, I said, same question would
be if you go and
you see the Mediterranean. You see the Mediterranean within thirty days, you
don't make another ברכה *berachah*. You see it once when you're not
Jewish, you convert, and then the day later you see it, do
you still make the, do you make the, do you make the
ברכה *bracha*? Or do you say how about תשחית *tashchis*, he shouldn't
go back? All right,
let's not go there. Anyway, it's an interesting question about which statuses
remain, stay with you after conversion. All right, anyway, if once he
was חיים *Chaim* it was a thousand plus two hundred, then changing
it to a straight loan obviously wouldn't work because then you have
a great way of always getting out of ריבית ribbit *ribbis*. Right
before I pay you back, we'll just change it all into a
new debt. So obviously once it started with a thousand, two hundred
once he was Jewish, you can't now change it into something else
because the interest has already accrued and that will accrue in the
future. Suppose halfway through the term of the loan, yeah, but, no,
right, but it doesn't say that. Even though it's true the interest
accrued as a non, it's true, that's part of the חידוש *chiddush*
here. Even though the interest accrued while he was still Christopher, and
when he was חיים *Chaim* there was no new interest, but the
very fact that it was framed at that moment as I owe
you a thousand dollars plus two hundred dollars interest, then that money
can't be paid even though there was no in, debt, new interest
accrued. Right, and that's part of the חידוש *chiddush*. Okay. Now, where
were we? גובה את הקרן וגובה את הריבית *Goveh es haker ve-goveh
es haribbis*. ואם אחר שנתגייר זקפן עליו במלוה גובה את הקרן ואינו
גובה את הריבית gove et hakeren ve-eino gove et haribbit. *Ve-im achar
shenisgayer zakfan alav bemilveh goveh es haker ve-eino goveh es haribbis*. וכן
נכרי שלוה מעות מישראל *Ve-chein nochri she-lavah maos mi-Yisrael*. Christopher borrowed money
from ראובן *Reuven* בריבית *beribbis* וזקפן עליו במלוה *ve-zakfan alav bemilveh*. Same
thing, except now Christopher owes ראובן *Reuven* a thousand plus two hundred
and turned it into a twelve hundred dollar loan. ונתגייר *Ve-nisgayer*. And
then he converted. אם עד שלא נתגייר זקפן עליו במלוה *Im ad
shelo nisgayer zakfan alav bemilveh*, if it changed to twelve hundred dollars
before he converted. and now he's Chaim and when he becomes Chaim
he owes straight twelve hundred dollars, גובה את הקרן וגובה את הריבית,
then he can pay Reuven the whole twelve hundred dollars. ואם משנתגייר
זקפה עליו במלווה, Ve'im mishe'nitgayer zakfah alav be'milveh, if however first he
converted and it was a thousand and two hundred and then he
changed it into a twelve hundred dollar loan, גובה את הקרן ואינו
גובה את הריבית, then he can only pay Reuven the principal, okay,
because then at the moment he became Chaim he owed him two
hundred dollars of interest, that two hundred dollars can't be paid. So
in that case if the- if changing it to the twelve hundred
dollars came after he became Chaim, then you can't pay him the-
then you would not pay Reuven the two hundred dollars. רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, Rabbi Yossi says no, in the second case,
נכרי שלווה מעות מישראל בריבית, nochri she'lavah maot miYisrael be'ribbit, in your
second case there where Christopher borrowed money and now he owes him
a thousand plus two hundred, בין כך ובין כך גובה את הקרן
וגובה את הריבית, bein kach u'vein kach goveh et ha'keren ve'goveh et
ha'ribbit, whether he changes it into the loan before or after, even
if after he became Chaim he made it from the thousand plus
two hundred into twelve hundred, he would still pay the full twelve
hundred. Now why? Why isn't that like Chaim is now paying Reuven,
you know, two hundred dollars that were initially tagged as ריבית ribbit.
money? So and you might think well this is just a more-
a way of getting you know whatever more money to the- for
Reuven, but no, let's Rava's going to say the reason. אמר רבא
אמר רב חסדא אמר רב הונא הלכה כרבי יוסי, Amar Rava amar
Rav Chisda amar Rav Huna halacha ke'Rabbi Yossi, we rule like Rabbi
Yossi. אמר רבא מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי, Amar Rava mai ta'ama de'Rabbi
Yossi, what's the reason of Rabbi Yossi? Why when Christopher is the
lender- oh sorry Christopher is the borrower, why does it matter you
know when the loan was changed before after conversion? But when Christopher
is the borrower you're always going to pay the full amount. Why
is that? כדי שלא יאמרו בשביל מעותיו נתגייר זה, kedei she'lo yomru
bishvil me'otav nitgayer zeh, because they shouldn't say, oh you know why
Christopher became Chaim? So that he wouldn't have to pay the full
twelve hundred dollars, right? Right, you see, Christopher now owes this Jew
all this interest money. Wait, if I convert I won't have to
pay the interest money! So therefore we say, I don't care now
whether you changed it you know before or after, you're going to
always have to pay him the full amount so people shouldn't say
that. Of course it's like having a real Jewish cup before you
convert it, you know... The authenticity of the גירות. geirut. Right, right,
oh my god, I just- I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I just gotta
tell this joke. So these two Jews are walking by this church
and there's a sign up and it says, five thousand dollars for
every Jew, you know, converted to Christianity. So Chaim and- so Reuven
and Shimon are looking at one another and they're saying like, oh
five thousand dollars, not bad, what should we do? Shall I go
in and convert you? You'll go in and convert me? So finally
they decide, you know, Shimon's going to go in and convert himself
and collect the money and he'll come back, he'll tell Reuven if
it worked and then Reuven'll decide what to do. So Shimon goes
in, Reuven's waiting, waiting, finally after two three hours Shimon comes out.
So Reuven says to him, nu nu what happened? Did you get
the money? So Shimon's like, that's all you Jews think about, money.
Alright, anyway, so- alright we'll have to go back and edit that
out of the tape. Alright anyway, so- so- see there's a reason
you come back for the דף. daf. You- alright anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara so the question is- alright that's what Rava said. So
if that's true though, it's interesting because how do we allow it?
No, it's very nice that people shouldn't say that he converted for
the wrong reason, but when Christopher converted he owed- and he became
Chaim, he owed a thousand plus two hundred and now we're changing
it into a loan and he's now going to pay the full
twelve hundred. Well, how do you do that? He actually- actually two
hundred was ריבית. ribbit Maybe it has to go with what Dov
said, because it's an old money that was owed, it wasn't new
interest that was accrued as a Jew, even though and even though
when he became Chaim conceptually it was a thousand plus two hundred,
it was two hundred that he en- that he in- that he
owed as a non-Jew. He never owed interest as a Jew. So
maybe that's why it's allowed. Of course even so me- and- and
you know and therefore some of these issues here are not מעיקר
הדין. me'ikar ha'din. Some of these issues here more about appearances, you
know, and at the end of the day it maybe you know
it is okay really technically to pay that if no new interest
was accrued as a Jew. The interesting point though is is that
if I was Christopher and I wanted to convert to get out
of paying the interest, then even according to Rabbi Yossi I would
just convert and I would never change the loan. I would never
agree to change it into a twelve hundred dollar loan, right? Rabbi
Yossi says it doesn't matter whether you changed it into the twelve
hundred dollar loan before or after you converted. But let's say you
didn't change it into a twelve hundred dollar loan at all? You
left it remain a thousand dollars plus two hundred, right? Which it
remain- maybe you'd still be paying but that's not explicit. The only
cases dealt with here is that you change the thousand plus two
hundred into twelve hundred and the question is did you do it
before you convert. when you pay that extra two hundred, even if
you didn't change it into a new loan, would that really be
a ריבית ribbit problem if it was not interest that was accrued
as a Jew? It was only interest that was accrued as a
non-Jew. Okay, let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, תנו רבנן,
rabbanan our Rabbis taught. שטר שכתוב בו ריבית, Shtar she-katuv bo ribbit,
you have a written document. The גמרא Gemara before talked about writing
out ריבית ribbit. in a שטר shtar. and how the lack of
shame that people have with that. Okay, so I have a document
that says that Eli owes me a thousand dollars plus five percent
interest weekly. Okay, so שטר שכתוב בו ריבית קונסין אותו ואינו גובה
לא את הקרן ולא את הריבית דברי רבי מאיר. shtar she-katuv bo
ribbit konesin oto ve-eino gove lo et hakeren ve-lo et haribbit divrei
Rabbi Meir. I want to now go and get Eli to pay
me a thousand dollars. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I'm sorry, we're
tearing up the whole שטר. shtar It's a שטר shtar. that has
an עבירה, aveirah, sort of actually embodied in it. Okay, you can't
use that שטר. shtar You were using this to do an עבירה,
aveirah, we toss it out. Now תוספות has an interesting question. Does
that mean that it loses its power of a שטר shtar. that
I cannot get from liens? Or does that mean that I can't
use it at all? And if I don't have separate witnesses to
prove that Eli owes me the money, then I'm without any evidence.
We totally tear up the שטר. shtar It's תוספות is in favor
of the second thing and it really sounds like that. There's no
mention here of liens. It sounds like you used this שטר shtar
to do this עבירה aveirah of lending with interest, we're going to
just tear it all up. Now it's interesting though, if I had
witnesses that I lent Eli money with interest, then I could still
use those witnesses to prove he owed me the principal and collect
the principal, right? But it's different when I concretize it and make
it physical evidence of the עבירה, aveirah, that piece of שטר shtar,
is that we're going to tear up and you can't even use
it even to collect the principal even for as evidence we're just
going to tear it up. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
Okay, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-Chachamim omrim, the
Rabbis say, גובה את הקרן ואינו גובה את הריבית. No, you can
still use it for the principal, you cannot use it for the
ריבית. ribbit I gotta tell you, I appreciate רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
position. It seems like it really compromises the integrity of the court
to recognize the document that has ריבית ribbit written in it to
collect the principal. And it would seem like it would really be
a good disincentive to lending with ריבית ribbit if you were to
tear up the שטר, shtar. right? So I really hear, sometimes רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir קנסות kenasot and גזירות gezerot go overboard, but this
one makes a lot of sense. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, במאי קמיפלגי, bemai kamiflegi, what do they debate? רבי מאיר
סבר קונסין היתר משום איסור. Rabbi Meir savar konasin heter mishum issur.
We fine the person for the היתר heter amount, the principal, because
of the forbidden amount, because the ריבית was forbidden, we're going to
fine him and not let him use it even for the principal
amount. רבנן סברי לא קונסין היתר משום איסור. Rabbanan savri lo konasin
heter mishum issur. No, we don't fine a person. Okay, now let's
see how this plays out. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught over
there in גיטין, Gittin, in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and elsewhere. שטרות
המוקדמים פסולים והמאוחרים כשרים. Shtarot hamukdamim pesulin ve-hamu'acharim kesherin. If you write
a document and you pre-date it prior to the loan, then it
is invalid. Why is it invalid? Because Eli borrows a thousand dollars
from me and instead of writing December whatever today is, sixth, we
write November first. Because we wrote November first, if Eli can't pay
me up, I'm going to be able to use to have liens
on property that he sold between November first and today and December
sixth, right? So some innocent person who bought property from Eli on
November first because he checked there was no outstanding loans against Eli,
he bought that property, now because I've pre-dated it I'm going to
be able to go and seize that property. That's the problem of
a pre-dated שטר. shtar So a pre-dated שטר shtar is invalid, but
a post-dated שטר shtar is kosher. So מוקדמים mukdamim are פסולים, pesulin,
why is a pre-dated one invalid? ניהי דלא גבי מזמן ראשון נגבי
מזמן שני. Nihi d'lo gove mizman rishon nigve mizman sheni. Why not
if we were to follow the Rabbis and not רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, just disallow the problematic part? Don't let me collect any liens
prior to December sixth, but let me collect the liens from today
on. Okay, there's an obvious reason why you can't do that. The
גמרא Gemara says, אמר ריש לקיש במחלוקת שנויה ורבי מאיר היא. amar
Reish Lakish bemachloket shnuya v'Rabbi Meir hi. So he says, fine, it's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if part of
the שטר shtar. is invalid, we tear up the whole שטר. shtar:
But there's a better answer. יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא רבנן. Yochanan amar
afilu teima rabbanan. No, no, no, even the רבנן rabbanan. who generally
disagree with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, here you understand why they wouldn't
want why they would tear up the שטר: shtar גזירה שמא יגבה
מזמן ראשון. gezeirah shema yigbeh mizman rishon. Because there's nothing in the
שטר shtar that makes it obvious that it was predated. The שטר
shtar doesn't say I lent money on December 5th, but we're saying
that this took place on November 1st. No, it says I lent
the money on November 1st. So there's no way we can say,
oh, we're going to disallow that part... we'll be tricked. Any שטר
shtar. we see like that, we're going to assume was properly dated.
So we have to throw out the whole שטר. shtar Okay, whereas
a שטר shtar, with interest, we can split it. It says you
borrowed $1,000 with 5% interest. So the evidence is in the שטר,
shtar so we can say we'll allow this part, we won't allow
that part. Okay. What does a... how does a predated שטר shtar.
work? Like, you have two dates there now? No, you don't. You
don't claim that you're predating it. You just predate it. You just
write on it, Eli borrowed $1,000 from me on November 1st, even
though you didn't, even though you borrowed it on December 7th or
whatever. Okay, so that's the point. There, there's no evidence in the
שטר. shtar We gotta throw the whole שטר shtar out. Here, the
שטר shtar, is clear what the terms are and we can accept
part and not accept another part. Yes. So that assumes you have
witnesses who in fact know the real date of the loan. The
very possibility that you might be able to split it assumes that
you do have those witnesses. And the גמרא'ס Gemara's response is, even
if you had those witnesses, it's way too dangerous to have this
document circulating around because this document hides that fact. So it's if
you get caught... Right, well, that's always if you get caught. Right,
if nobody knows it's a predated שטר, shtar you get away with
it. But if you get caught, what are we going to do?
You're correct. So it has to start with the fact that you
got caught and we have witnesses. And the answer is, we cannot
split the שטר shtar because the שטר shtar, is... it doesn't reflect
that and it's a dangerous document to have around. So yes, even
though you're now caught there, and even if we were to want
to split it, we can't, so we're going to throw the whole
thing out. Okay, so absolutely. All right, so now that's why that's
true. That would even be the רבנן. Now let's have a story.
ההוא גברא דמשכניה פרדיסא לחבריה. Hahu gavra demashkanei pardisa lechavrei. Somebody, you
know, put into collateral a garden, רש"י Rashi says it means a
vineyard, to his friend. Meaning, so he borrowed money from, you know,
Eli there borrowed money from me and I am now taking possession
as collateral of his vineyard. And this will be, you know, one
of those things of משכנתא דנכייתא. mashkanta de-nachita. I do some, you
know, nominal deduction of the loan and I'm eating the grapes of
the vineyard while he's waiting to pay me back the loan. Okay,
remember that from before? אכלה תלת שני. Achala telat shani. I now
have been eating the grapes for three years in Eli's vineyard. Wait,
you can't leave, I gotta pay you back your loan. I'm teasing.
אמר ליה אי מזבנת לה ניהלי. Amar lei i mizabnat lah nihali.
So I say, there, now I go to Eli and I say,
Eli, I got a business proposition for you. I've been eating grapes
in your vineyard for three years. If you sell me your vineyard
at my... at my price, okay, מוטב, mutav, you'll be in good
shape. ואי לאו, V'ee lav, if you refuse to sell me your
vineyard, you know what I'm going to do? כבשינא ליה לשטר משכנתא,
Kavshina lei leshtar mashkanta, I'll hide the fact that I had lent
you the money originally and I'll just claim, why have I been
eating stuff for three years? Because I bought it from him and
I have a חזקה. chazaka. ואמינא לקוחה היא בידי. V'amina lekucha hi
beyadi. I'll say I purchased it from you three years ago. So
I am using that as leverage to get him to sell it
to me, which he doesn't want to sell it or sell it
at my price or whatever. He's in a real bind, okay? Because
I now am forcing him to sell, he has few options. You
know what he does? אזל אקנייה לבנו קטן. Azal akneiya livno katan.
He went and he transferred the title to his... to his minor
son, or his wife, or whatever he did. והדר זבנה ניהליה. V'hadar
zabnah nihali. And then he sold it to me. So he sold
it to me after he no longer owned it. So he was
able to get his money back, right? He was able to, you
know, whatever, get out of the whole situation. Okay. So let's see.
So he... so fine. That's the story. Now here's the question. Now
it's discovered the whole ruse. You can go if you want. It's
discovered the whole ruse that he did. Okay, he did that whole
ruse. That's discovered. And now, but what has he... how did he
benefit from it? It was a ruse, it was going to be
discovered. He benefited from the following way. There's now a document that
I bought it from him, right, just now, I bought it from
him recently. So I can no longer claim that I bought it
from him three years ago. Right? My whole leverage was I was
going to claim I bought it from you three years ago, I've
been eating the fruit for three years, it's a חזקה, chazaka, etc.
He says, no, if you did that, why did you think you
had to buy it from me yesterday? So now, so yes, the
ruse is discovered, he completely undermined my leverage. So what's left? So
what's left is he took the money from me when I bought
it from him. Okay. And now I want that money back. And
here becomes all of this very fascinating, complicated case to get to
the following question. I want that money back. When we had that
document of sale, which now turned out to be a false sale,
it says he sold me the fields for $1,000. Okay. And it
also says, a standard document of sale also says, if... Whatever reason
this sale doesn't go through, like the land was stolen, the land
wasn't mine, creditors come, I will reimburse you. Okay, that's implicit in
the document of sale that there's אחריות. achrayus. Okay, so I gave
him a thousand dollars for his vineyard, he gave it to me.
So now I've lost my leverage because it's obvious that I didn't
own it three years ago. And now he says, ha-ha-ha, I transferred
it to my minor son. Okay, but fine, give me back the
thousand dollars. Well, I don't have the thousand dollars on me. So,
can I use this document that I'm entitled to get reimbursed, obviously
it was a false sale, can I use this document as if
it was a שטר חוב shtar chov that gives me liens? And
can I actually take not just the property he has on his
person, but actually take property that he has sold in the interim?
It's very complicated. What? Not to your son. That would be funny.
You definitely give it to my minor son's. Right, right, right, right,
yes, but it would only be liens of stuff that occurred after
the sale, right? Right, that's a good point. Okay, so זביני, zvini,
it's a complicated case, but bottom line is, a document the simple
way to think about it is, a document put all the complexity
aside. A document of sale and it turns that has אחריות, achrayus,
which means that you can get reimbursed if for whatever reason the
field is taken from you. And it turns out I never owned
the field to begin with. Does that document of sale which now
entitles you to get your money back and whatever, also give you
liens? Is it like a שטר חוב shtar chov and does it
give you liens? Okay, so that you can collect not just from
me, but from people I sold property to. Okay, yes, what happened
to the first part of this story, the money that's still owed?
It's still owed and but the lender ate three years of produce.
Right, how does that get balanced? Yeah, so that has to do
with the stuff before about משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta d'surayya, maybe there was
some nominal reduction of the loan. So, okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, זביני ודאי לא הוו זביני. zvini vadai lo
havei zvini. The sale certainly wasn't good, it was owned by the
minor son. זוזי כמלוה בשטר דמו. zuzei k'milveh b'shtar damu. Now the
money that was paid for the vineyard and you had this document
of sale, so now the money has to be retrieved, is that
like it was lent with a שטר, shtar, וגבי מנכסי משעבדי, v'gavei
minichsei meshubadei, and you can collect from stuff that you have a
lien on? או דילמא כמלוה על פה דמו ואינו גבי מנכסי משעבדי?
o dilma k'milveh al peh damu v'eino gavei minichsei meshubadei? Or since
we say that the שטר, shtar he never owned the property when
he was selling it, the שטר shtar. was a meaningless שטר. shtar
And since you're selling property you don't have, the שטר shtar, is
a meaningless שטר, shtar. it doesn't give you liens. Okay, you get
your money back because it was a מקח טעות, mekach taus, but
it was a false sale, but it doesn't give you liens. Okay,
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, ולאו היינו דרבי אסי? v'lav haynu d'Rabbi Assi?
Isn't this Rabbi Assi? דאמר רבי אסי, d'amar Rabbi Assi, Rabbi Assi
says: מודה בשטר שכתבו אינו צריך לקיימו וגובה מנכסי משעבדי. modeh b'shtar
shektavo eino tzarich l'kaymo v'goveh minichsei meshubadei. It's not at all clear
why how this case is relevant. The גמרא Gemara will object in
a moment. But basically, David here comes and says Dov you owe
me a thousand dollars here's the שטר. shtar And the שטר shtar.
is not validated. If I admit, yes, I do owe you that
money, David can now collect even the liens, even from people that
purchased my property in the interim. Now, somebody will come along and
say, what are you talking about? I don't believe that's a good
שטר. shtar, Maybe it's a forgery. So what do I care that
Dov validated it? You're trying to collect the property from me! You're
not trying to collect the money from Dov! But nevertheless, even if
I am the basis of validating the שטר, shtar I'm the one
who owes the money, and it's going to impact the people who
purchased the field from me. Nevertheless, he can still use it to
collect those liens even though the validation comes from me. Now what
the heck that has to do with our case it's not clear
as it's a מלוה על פה. milveh al peh. Right, it seems
like the point is, is that here's a שטר shtar that is
somewhat questionable, it hasn't been externally validated, and we're still going to
use it to collect liens. So by some loose analogy, this document
of sale, which is not really a sale because you didn't own
the property, but nevertheless, since money did change hands, will be enough
to collect from liens. Okay? And you have oral testimony, so it's
like a מלוה על פה. milveh al peh. I understand, but you're
still collecting from liens. So the גמרא Gemara says, but there's an
obvious big difference between them. So אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava,
Rava said back, מי דמי? mi dami? What type of comparison is
it? התם ניתן ליכתב. hasam nisan l'hikatev. There, there really was a
debt, and the שטר shtar. was a legitimate שטר. shtar. Okay, it
hasn't been validated yet. It's only been validated based on the borrower.
But nobody is questioning that if it was written, it's a legitimate
שטר. shtar So therefore there are liens. הכא לא ניתן ליכתב. hacha
lo nisan l'hikatev. Here, you sold property that wasn't yours. The שטר
shtar never was valid to begin with. It was a meaningless document.
So how could we say that this document has liens? יתיב מרימר
וקאמר לה להאי שמעתא. yasiv Mareimar v'ka-amar lah l'hai shmayta. So Mareimar
was sitting and telling over Rava's idea about whether it should have
been written, shouldn't have been written. We're going to see how this
is relevant to us, it's going to circle back. אמר ליה רבינא
למריימר. amar lei Ravina leMareimar. So Ravina said to Mareimar, אלא הא
דאמר רבי יוחנן גזירה שמא יגבה מזמן ראשון ela ha de'amar Rabbi
Yochanan gezeirah shema yigbeh mizman rishon here's where we circle back, right?
The reason we throw out a predated שטר shtar. is that you
might come to use it to collect the liens from earlier on,
right? That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. That's why we throw
out a predated שטר. shtar That you'll come to use it from
the date in the שטר shtar where the liens are not yet
valid. נימא לא ניתן ליכתב. neima lo nitan likateiv. I don't understand.
Rather than giving this idea גזירה שמא, gezeirah shema, technically it would
be valid and usable from the date of the loan, but we're
afraid you're going to use it from the predated date. Why not
say you had no right to write the שטר shtar, altogether? And
that's why there are no liens. According to רבא, Rava, רבא Rava
wants to throw out this document of sale when the guy didn't
own the property, and basically say if you had no right to
write the שטר, shtar. you know, then there are no liens. So
say that about a predated שטר. shtar The reason there are no
liens is you had no right to write it. אמר ליה הכי
השתא. amar lei hachi hashta. What type of a comparison is that?
התם נהי דלא ניתן ליכתב מזמן ראשון, hatam nehi delo nitan likateiv
mizman rishon, you didn't have any basis to write it from the
predated date, אבל ניתן ליכתב מזמן שני. aval nitan likateiv mizman sheini.
You were entitled to write it from the date of the loan.
Okay, so again, there are big differences. There's a big difference between
a שטר shtar that has yet to be validated or a שטר
shtar that does represent a loan but was predated, but at least
fundamentally the שטר shtar is valid, you know, should have been written
on the loan, to a שטר shtar. of sale that had, you
know, on property you didn't own. A sale document on property you
didn't own is complete garbage and it shouldn't entitle you to any
liens. So the גמרא says, okay, אלא הא דתניא ela ha detanya
that which we taught, ולשבח קרקעות כיצד. u'leshevach karka'ot keitzad. Okay, this
is a principle you might remember this, which is that when creditors
come to collect from property that I sold, right, they come to
collect their liens, they cannot collect from things that, debts that accrue
that they don't know how much it would be that I, you
know, that I might wind up owing because the amount is not
specific because it's not fair to the people I sold the property
to. So one category of this is שבח קרקעות. shevach karka'ot. What
does that mean? Let's take a look. הרי שגזל שדה מחבירו. harei
shegazal sadeh meichaveiro. Let's say it turns out that I stole a
field ומכרה לאחר umachra leachair and sold it to another person והשביחה.
ve'ishpicha. And then, so I stole a field, I sold it, you
know, to Gloria. Gloria improved it. והרי היא יוצאת מתחת ידו. ve'harei
hi yotzet mitachat yado. And now the original owner has come, proven
his title, taken it away from Gloria. Gloria now wants back from
me her thousand dollars of the purchase price plus the five hundred
dollars that she spent on improving it. So the five hundred dollars
she spent on improving it is שבח קרקעות. shevach karka'ot. Now she
can collect the thousand dollars from liens, from people that I sold
property to, because they knew I sold a piece of property ואחריות.
ve'achrayut. They knew to protect themselves against a thousand dollars of the
purchase price. But she cannot collect the extra five hundred dollars from
those other people, because they did not know how much, you know,
improvements would be made. So since it was a non-specified amount, I
have to pay Gloria back, but it's not fair that the liens
extend that far. Okay, כשהוא גובה גובה את הקרן מנכסים משועבדים. k'shehu
goveh goveh et hakeren minichasim meshu'abadim. She can collect the principal amount
from liens והשבח ve'hashevach but the amount that she added גובה מנכסים
בני חורין goveh minichasim benei chorin and only from unencumbered property, property
that I own. Anyway, the relevance for all of this is, is
that this is our case! I sold a piece of property to
Gloria with a bill of sale which clearly was bogus because it
wasn't my property. And she is using this bill of sale to
collect liens, to collect the principal back from people I sold property
to. So here you see a bogus bill of sale, sale of
a property I don't own, can still be used to get liens,
to create liens, to get reimbursed. Is that clear that that was
our basic case, right? Remember our basic case was, the guy who
transferred the property to his son and it turned out whatever blah
blah blah can that document of sale at least entitle the person
to liens to get reimbursed. So the גמרא says, נימא לא ניתן
ליכתב. neima lo nitan likateiv. That shouldn't have been written. Right? Because
that was a bogus bill of sale. So why is, does it
entitle Gloria to the liens if I didn't own the property to
begin with? הכי השתא. hachi hashta. Now what's the comparison? התם אי
למאן דאמר ניחא ליה דלא ניקרי גזלנא אי למאן דאמר ניחא ליה
דליקום בהימנותיה. hatam ei leman de'amar nicha lei delo nikrai gazlana ei
leman de'amar nicha lei deleikum beheimanutei. There, we assume when I basically
sold that thing to Gloria that I would want to make sure
that she was reimbursed if it ever turned out not... by the
way, I didn't even necessarily consciously steal the field, right? You know,
sometimes there's all these questions of title and it turns out it
wasn't mine, but whatever the case would be, I know when I
sold it to her if it ever turned out not... If it
ever turned out that it was stolen or if it was discovered
that it was stolen, and I would want to make sure she
was reimbursed. Why? Because I wouldn't want her to go around saying,
"Oh, Dov's a גזלן, gazlan, besides that he was גוזל gozel the
field, he was גוזל gozel me, you know? He took my money
for it and he never paid me back." So either I don't
want to be called a גזלן, gazlan, אי למאן דאמר לא ניחא
ליה דליכא ביה מנוולא, ee leman de'amar lo nicha lei deleika beih
menuvala, or forget, you know that, or, you know, either or that
like he kept his trust with me and at least he paid
me back, you know? So we don't want her upset about what
happened, I don't want her upset about what happened. If she's gonna
go around telling everybody how I stole this field, or she's gonna
go around telling everybody how I didn't even reimburse her after the
field was taken from her. So there, I want her to have
those liens, and I want to be able to pay her back
if something goes wrong because I want to protect my reputation. So
מפיס ליה למרי ומוקים ליה בשטרא. mafiyes lei le-marei u-mukim lei b'shtara.
So in that case, right, I will basically try to, you know,
uphold the שטר. shtar Now what רש"י Rashi says is what מפיס
ליה למרי mafiyes lei le-marei actually means is that I will actually
go ahead and if it turns out it's stolen, I'm actually going
to try first of all to try to get the original owner
to pay him off. I said, "Oh, it turned out I stole
it, fine. Let me pay you off and buy the field from
you now so Gloria can keep it so she doesn't go around
spreading a bad reputation about me." And if I can't do that
and the field is taken from her, I want the שטר shtar
to be valid. I want her to get reimbursed. So I have
a vested interest there in ensuring she's reimbursed. So there, even though
it was a bogus bill of sale, the שטר shtar in a
certain way was genuine. I wanted her to have those rights. But
הכא, hacha, in this case where the field was transferred to the
minor son and the guy was getting trying to get out of
being exploited, לאו לרווחא מיניה קא מכוין. lav revucha minei ka michavein.
שטרא מקיים ליה? shtara mekayem leh? He's trying to get out of
selling the field to me. He's trying to get out of my
exploiting him, okay? So he doesn't want this bill of sale to
be used against him, right, to go ahead and be a valid
bill. He is trying to, it's intentionally a bogus thing in order
to get out of the way I'm exploiting him. So in this
case, it's not enough that factually it was a bogus bill of
sale, it has to be that the whole thing was a ruse.
Even if factually it was a bogus bill of sale, if you
wanted it to be legitimate and to have power, that could still
create liens. But in this case where the whole thing was a
ruse and it was a ruse done to get out of my
exploiting him, so he says the שטר shtar isn't really a שטר
shtar also. The שטר is also just part of the whole ruse
and therefore it does not entitle you to any liens. Okay, that
was a little complicated, but we will now pick up tomorrow.